Thomas Salmon MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Thomas Salmon MD Papers
1897 - 1940
This collection contains the papers of Thomas Salmon, who was a leading pioneer in the field of mental hygiene. The collection is missing information, including series, and needs to be reprocessed.
2.92 linear feet (7 boxes)
Salmon, Thomas W. (Thomas William), 1876-1927
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1975.0001
Unknown.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Thomas William Salmon (1876-1927) was born in Lansingburg, New York, on January 6, 1876. After graduating from Lansingburg Academy, he taught school for two years and then attended Albany Medical College, receiving his degree in 1899. He practiced medicine until his untimely death on August 13, 1927 in a drowning accident while sailing on the Long Island Sound. Surviving were his wife of more than 27 years, Helen Potter Ashley, and their six children.
Dr. Salmon was a leading pioneer in the field of mental hygiene. His first position was as bacteriologist studying an epidemic of diphtheria at Willard State Hospital for the Insane in Ovid, New York. His interest in psychiatry was kindled at Willard while working with Dr. William L. Russell, already a leader in the field. In 1903, Dr. Salmon accepted a commission in the United States Marine Hospital Service (the present United States Public Health Service) and became especially interested in the sailors who were patients at the U.S.M.H.S. general hospitals, which led him to advocate for a hospital for deep sea fishermen.
One of his most notable achievements on the P.H.S. was the establishment of the Ellis Island psychiatric service for immigrants. In 1905, Dr. Salmon was assigned to the immigration service and worked there for the next six years. In 1911, at the request of the New York State Commission in Lunacy, he was given a leave of absence from the service in order to serve as chief medical examiner of the New York State Board of Alienists. Because of his work with immigrants and the New York State Board, Dr. Salmon became director of special studies of the National Committee for Mental Hygiene in 1912. In 1915, the National Committee could afford to hire him permanently, so Dr. Salmon resigned from the Public Health Service, from which he had been on leave since 1912, and became the medical director of the National Committee.
During the First World War, Dr. Salmon did what he considered to be his most important work. He developed a plan for, and then implemented, the organization of neuropsychiatric units for the Army and the Navy. The goals of these units were the prevention or early treatment of mental disorders in the military services and the elimination of mentally disordered recruits.
After the war, Dr. Salmon became involved in academic psychiatry. He accepted a position as professor of psychiatry at Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons. As a professor, he carried through the plans of creating a psychiatric institute in conjunction with the University by founding the State Psychiatric Institute at Columbia. In addition to his teaching, Dr. Salmon was a member of leading national and New York societies of neurology and psychiatry and was a president of the American Psychiatric Association and the New York Psychiatrical Society. He was the author of one book and numerous journal articles.
Salmon, Thomas W. (Thomas William), 1876-1927; Ellis Island Hospital; National Committee for Mental Hygiene; Post-traumatic stress disorder; United States. Marine Hospital Service; United States. Public Health Service; United States -- Emigration and immigration; World War, 1914-1918
This collection contains the papers of Thomas Salmon, who was a leading pioneer in the field of mental hygiene. The collection is missing information, including series, and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Biographical material, Undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1897 - 1898 (Box 1)
  - Biographical material, Undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and professional material, Public Health and Marine Hospital Service, 1901 - 1907 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, C. Beers and Rockefeller Foundation, National Committee for Mental Hygiene, Undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and professional material on immigration, State Commission in Lunacy, 1912 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Public Health and Marine Hospital Service, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and material on immigration, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and professional material, Immigration, U.S. Public Health Service, Floating Hospital, 1913 - 1914 (Box 1)
  - Professional material, Immigration, State boards of control, 1915 (Box 2)
  - Professional material, N.C.M.H., Almshouses, 1916 (Box 2)
  - Professional material, 1917 (Box 2)
  - Professional material and correspondence, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Professional material and correspondence, 1918 - 1919 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence to Mrs. Salmon, Undated (Box 2)
  - Biographical material, 1917 - 1938 (Box 3)
  - Documents on World War I, c. 1917 (Box 3)
  - Documents on World War I, 1919 (Box 3)
  - Documents, 1920 (Box 3)
  - Biographical material, Undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and professional documents, 1923; 1940 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and other miscellaneous material, Undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1921 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1922 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1922 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1924 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1927 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1928 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930 - 1934 (Box 4)
  - Reprints, Undated (Box 5)
  - Letters to Helen Ashley Salmon, 1918 (Box 6)
  - Letters to Helen Ashley Salmon, 1918 (Box 6)
  - Letters to Helen Ashley Salmon, 1918 (Box 6)
  - Letters to Helen Ashley Salmon, 1918 (Box 6)
  - Letters to Helen Ashley Salmon, 1919 (Box 6)
  - Letters to Helen Ashley Salmon, 1919; Undated (Box 6)
  - Guide to the letters of Thomas W. Salmon to Helen Ashley Salmon prepared by J. Theodore Johnson, Jr., 2012 (Box 6)
  - Background information and copies of photographs of Thomas W. Salmon, Undated (Box 6)
  - Copies of books gifted by Thomas W. Salmon to his daughter, Undated (Box 6)
  - Pamphlets related to the Salmon lecture series, Undated (Box 7)